Murray Bennett Papers
Murray Bennett Papers
1842-1965
Bennett, Murray.
5.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American stage actor, director, poet. Incoming correspondence (1875, 1909-1961), letter books, Bennett's subject file, theater programs, photographs, manuscript poems, and clippings. Includes correspondence of Charles E. Herring, Archibald Rutledge, Sybil Thorndike, and Estelle Winwood, and others.
148844
Biographical History
Murray Bennett (1896-?) was an American stage actor, director, and poet.
Born in 1896 in Charleston, South Carolina, he graduated from Newton Military Academy in 1913, and the American Academy of Dramatic Arts in 1921. Bennett made his first broadway appearance in The Green Goddess with George Arliss that same year. From that time on his acting career was assured and he appeared throughout the twenties and thirties in such plays as Roseanne, Hamlet, Love in a Mist, and The Vinegar Tree. By the 1940's Bennett was a veteran actor. One of his greatest roles was in Rain, which appeared in 1945. Two years later he bought a small farm on the Carolina coast. However, he continued to pursue his career, appearing in summer stock, directing various community theatres and a radio program. In 1956, he again appeared on Broadway in Cat on a Hot Tin Roof.
In addition to his acting career, Bennett also was a poet. He published many sonnets, as well as a volume of poems titled Invisible Pursuit, and was an active member of the Poetry Society of America.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Murray Bennett Papers include correspondence, an album, photographs, programs, souvenirs, manuscripts and published materials.
Correspondence includes incoming and outgoing correspondence as well as letters to and from others. The outgoing correspondence includes two letter books as well as loose letters. The letter classified as "to and from others" was written by Mr. Bennett's father in 1875.
Subject files contains an album of theatre personalities, photographs, programs and souvenirs. Also included are files Mr. Bennett set up which pertain to a person or place in which he was interested, such as Rupert Brooke, Edna St. Vincent Millay, or Tahiti.
Manuscripts consists of poems by W. Bennett and poems by others. Mr. Bennett's poems are undated.
Published material includes books, magazines and newspaper clippings.
Arrangement of the Collection
Incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically by author. Outgoing correspondence is filed chronologically. Subject files are arranged in alphabetical order by name or subject; when necessary the materials have been further arranged in chronological order. Published material is arranged alphabetically by type and, within that, by title, except for newspaper clippings which are arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Popular culture; Radio, television, film; Bennett, Murray.; Herring, Charles Edward.; Rutledge, Archibald Hamilton, 1883-1973.; Thorndike, Sybil, Dame, 1882-1976.; Winwood, Estelle.; Actors -- United States.; Poets, American.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Letter books.; Photographs.; Poems.; Programs (documents); Actors.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Murray Bennett, 1964.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - Arliss, George, 1922 (Box 1)
    - Armistead, J.D.M., 1917-1923 (Box 1)
    - Bennett, Murray (Sr.), 1932; second typescript copy (Box 1)
    - Bennett, William B. (uncle), 1903 (Box 1)
    - Herring, Charles E., 1918-1922; undated (Box 1)
    - Myers, Ida G., 1916-1918; 1920,; 1923,; 1925,; 1929-1930,; undated (Box 1)
    - Norris, Charles H., 1920 (Box 1)
    - Rutledge, Archibald, 1950; 1961,; undated (Box 1)
    - Thorndike, Dame Sybil, 1935 (Box 1)
    - Winwood, Estelle, 1924; 1935-1936,; 1941,; undated (Box 1)
  - Outgoing
    - Letterbook, 1909-1910 (Box 1)
    - Letterbook, 1910-1913; 1919-1920,; 1922,; 1950,; 1961 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - To and from others
    - Murray Bennett, Sr., 1875 (Box 1)
- Subject file
  - Album, Theatre Personalities (Box 2)
  - Allen, Harvey, 1923; 1929,; 1934,; 1949 (Box 2)
  - Brooke, Rupert, 1934; 1965 (Box 2)
  - Ficke, Arthur Davison, 1922 (Box 2)
    See also Millay, Edna St. Vincent
  - Forbes-Robertson, Sir Johnston, 1937; 1940,; undated (Box 2)
  - Heyward, Dubose, 1927; 1935,; undated (Box 2)
  - Hobby, a book of cigar bands, 1907 (Box 2)
  - Millay, Edna St. Vincent, 1927-1928; 1930-1931,; 1940-1942,; 1951,; 1963 (Box 2)
  - Miss Thompson / W. Somerset Maugham, 1921; 1945 (Box 2)
  - Mitchell, John Ames (Box 2)
  - Hall, James Norman (Box 3)
  - Osborne, Thomas Mott, 1924 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1889; 1900-1901,; 1904,; 1922,; 1956,; 1960,; undated (Box 3)
  - Programs, 1914; 1916-1919,; 1921-1923,; 1926,; 1928,; 1937-1940,; undated; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Sargent, Franklin H., 1915; 1920,; 1921,; undated (Box 3)
  - Souvenirs, 1892; 1906,; undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Tahiti, 1914; 1919-1920,; 1921,; undated (Box 3)
  - Wylie, Elinor, 1922; 1929 (Box 3)
- Manuscripts
  - Poems by
    - from Invisible Pursuit (Box 3)
  - Poems by others
    - Bennett, Isaac S. (Mr. Bennett's grandfather), to a cousin, 1842 (Box 3)
- Published material
  - Books about
    - Dictionary of International Biography, 1963 (Box 4)
    - The Golden Year, 1960 (Box 4)
    - International Who's Who in Poetry, Vol. I, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Books by others
    - American Poetry, 1922 (Box 4)
    - An April Elegy / Ficke, Arthur Davison, 1917 (Box 4)
    - Aria Da Capo / Millay, Edna St. Vincent, autographed, 1920 (Box 4)
    - Battle and Other Poems / Gibson, Wilfred, Wilson, 1916 (Box 5)
    - Body of This Death / Bogan, Louise, autographed, 1923 (Box 5)
    - The Collected Poems of James Elroy Flecker / Flecker, 1916 (Box 5)
    - Dark Summers / Bogan, Louise (Box 5)
    - Death in Venice / Mann, Thomas, 1930 (Box 5)
    - The Door of Dreams / Rittenhouse, Jesse, 1918 (Box 5)
    - The Gay Twenties / Trewin, 1958 (Box 5)
    - A Glossary of Words and Phrases / Bartlett, 1848 (Box 6)
    - Last Poems / Wylie, Elinor, 1943 (Box 6)
    - The Limits of Art / Cairns, ed., 1948 (Box 6)
    - Little Book of Modern Verse / Rittenhouse, ed., 1913 (Box 6)
    - Little Henrietta, Reese, Licette W., autographed, 1927 (Box 7)
    - Mother Goose's Nursery Ryhmes /, 1897 (Box 7)
    - Mystic Isles of the South Seas / O'Brien, Frederick, 1921 (Box 7)
    - The New Poetry / Monroe, ed., 1918 (Box 7)
    - Opera Cavalcade, 1938 (Box 7)
    - Others / Kreymborg, ed., 1917 (Box 8)
    - The Oxford Book of English Verse, 1915 (Box 8)
    - Picture Show / Sasoon, Seigfried, 1920 (Box 8)
    - Rivers to the Sea / Teasdale, Sara, 1916 (Box 8)
    - A Saga of a Paper Mill / Pratt, Lawrence, 1935 (Box 8)
    - The Second Book of Modern Verse / Rittenhouse, ed., 1919 (Box 8)
    - Selected Poems / Vinal, Harold, autographed, 1948 (Box 8)
    - Songs of the Field / Ledwidge, Thomas, 1916 (Box 9)
    - Spicewood / Reese, Licette Woodworth, 1920 (Box 9)
    - Twinkletoes: A Tale of Chinatown, Burke, Thomas, 1918 (Box 9)
    - Verse / Adelaide Crapsey, 1922 (Box 9)
    - Vigils / Sassoon, Seigfried, 1936 (Box 9)
    - White April / Reese, Licette W., 1930 (Box 9)
    - Wonders of Italy / Fathroso, Joseph, ed., 1930 (Box 9)
  - Magazines
    - Putnam's Monthly, September 1853 (Box 10)
    - The Theatre
      - June to Christmas, 1907, 5 folders (Box 10)
      - April, 1908 (Box 10)
      - May, 1908 (Box 10)
      - March, 1909 (Box 10)
      - March, 1910 (Box 10)
      - April, 1910 (Box 10)
      - October, 1910 (Box 10)
      - November, 1910 (Box 10)
      - November, 1913 (Box 10)
      - October, 1914 (Box 10)
      - March, 1915 (Box 10)
      - May, 1915 (Box 11)
      - December, 1915 (Box 11)
      - May, 1916 (Box 11)
    - The Westminster Review, January, 1891; July, 1871; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Newspaper clippings about
    - Miscellaneous, 1945; 1947 (Box 11)
  - Newspaper clippings about others
    - Miscellaneous, 1916; 1921,; 1923,; 1938,; undated (Box 11)